Finding Aid for Financial Operations (University of Michigan) records, 1837-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Financial Operations (University of Michigan) records
1837-2004
1915-1990
University of Michigan. Financial Operations.
87167 BImu Bimu B8 2
Records generated by administrators and offices charged with the financial activities of the University, including Secretary and Vice-President Shirley W. Smith and Controller and Assistant Secretary John C. Christensen; include general University financial records; records of land; trust fund records; proposed development and construction projects; operating records of buildings, divisions and other units.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
35 linear feet
52 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
Material from the Financial Operations office has been received in numerous accessions, the first in 1952. The largest quantity of material was received in 1980; the most recent in 1982. [Donor no. 2942 ].
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The records are open to research, except for records in boxes 29-35, which are restricted until July 1, 2029.
The financial records of the University have been maintained in a number of different offices. Prior to the Civil War, the Regents authorized two University officers to retain financial records, the Treasurer and the Regent's Secretary. While the lines of authority were indistinct, generally the Treasurer was responsible for the actual collection or disbursement of funds, while the Secretary kept duplicate but more detailed records of transactions which he used to carry out his informal responsibility to serve as auditor and business manager. This basic arrangement was maintained and proved adequate until the twentieth century.
In 1908, however, the laxness of the accounting procedures became apparent when the state attorney general sharply criticized the University for maintaining at least one special petty cash fund which did not appear in the regular University financial records. The criticism, along with other issues, led to the resignation of the Secretary. In 1909 Shirley W. Smith was appointed Secretary to the Regents, and was given a mandate to overhaul the University's accounting procedures and policies.
Smith concluded that proper financial control required the centralization of operations in one office, and began the slow process of making all University fiscal matters flow through either himself or his subordinates. A central purchasing office was created, and the care of the university's physical plant, a major item of expense, was centralized under the Superintendent of Buildings and Grounds. When the University began a massive construction program in 1921, it was determined that all financial transactions regarding the numerous projects were to be processed by the Secretary's office. By the late 1920's all University department accounting records flowed into the Secretary's office. Recognizing the increasing financial responsibilities that their Secretary bore, the Regents in 1927 changed Smith's title to Secretary and Business Manager.
When Alexander Grant Ruthven was appointed University President in 1929, he was determined to reorganize the University's administration along the lines of a private corporation. As part of that reorganization, Smith in 1930 was named Vice-President and Secretary in charge of Business and Finance. Along with the new title, came a new and expanded mandate for Smith and his subordinates. The Treasurer's Office was abolished in 1931. Smith's office became responsible for accounting, purchasing, investments, cash management, buildings and grounds, construction, and services such as printing, stores and housing, all this in addition to the responsibilities incumbent upon the office as Secretary to the Regents.
The day to day financial operations of the unit were controlled by John C. Christensen. Hired by Smith in 1914 with the title Assistant Secretary, Christensen became Controller and Assistant Secretary when Smith was made a Vice-President. Among his many responsibilities, Christensen oversaw four financial units: accounting, purchasing, cashier and investments. The accounting unit was led by the Chief Accountant.
The retirements of Christensen in 1944 and Smith in 1945 led to a restructuring of the positions they had held. Robert P. Briggs, who succeeded Smith as Vice-President, was responsible only for the financial aspects of Smith's position. Herbert G. Watkins, who replaced Christensen, was made responsible for Smith's Secretarial duties and was given the title Secretary to the University. Technically, Watkins still reported to Briggs, but their responsibilities were both distinct and generally unrelated. This fact was recognized by the Regents in 1959 when the Secretary's office was reassigned to report directly to the University President, rather than through the Vice-President for Business and Finance.
In response to the ever expanding volume of operations created by the University's post 1945 growth, the lines of authority running from the Vice-President for Business and Finance became increasingly distinct and departmentalized. The Controllers Office became responsible for overseeing several operations, including that of the Accounting Office. In 1966, a reorganization by the new University Controller, Howard Cottrell, moved the Payroll Office as a unit from under the Chief Accountant. In addition, the sponsored research grant and contract administration function moved into the Accounting Department from the Office of the Assistant Controller and Business Manager for Sponsored Research. The small staff remaining in that office became the Office of Contract Review reporting to an Assistant to the Controller. In 1966 the Vice-President for Business and Finance title was changed to Vice-President and Chief Financial Officer. In subsequent years, the separate accounting systems for the Institute for Social Research, Food Stores, Law Club, and University Hospital were also incorporated into the central systems of the Accounting Department.
During academic year 1980-1981 the Accounting Office's name was changed to Financial Operations. The Chief Accountant's title was changed to Director.
Summary Contents List
General University Financial Records Boxes 1-6, 26, 31-34 Outsize Volumes 1-11, 17-19, and 48-51
Trust Fund Records Boxes 6-7
Records of Land, Proposed Development and Construction Boxes 8-14 outsize Volumes 12 and 52
Operating Records of Buildings, Divisions and other Units Boxes 15-22, and 27-28 Outsize Volumes 13-16, 20-27, and 47
Miscellaneous Reports, Studies and Volumes Boxes 18-19, and 28 Outsize Volumes 28-46
Accounting Office Records Boxes 22-23
Annual Audits of Student Organizations Box 24
Photographs Box 25
Correspondence Boxes 29-31
Student Fee Rates Box 34
U-M Economic Impact Box 35
The records of Financial Operations date from 1837 to 1982, primarily after 1910. The 27 linear feet of manuscript material, 52 oversized volumes and one reel of microfilm reflect not only the financial records normally associated with an accounting office, but also the broad range of subjects which became a concern under the leadership of Shirley Smith. What would eventually become Financial Operations may have served as a records storage office for many of the other units under Smith's control. In any event, Financial Operations became the guardian of a wide variety of records, documenting the University in a number of ways not normally expected of an accounting service.
Of particular note, the collection contains a variety of different record formats. Bound materials, in the form of books, are included in the boxes and when numbering more than one, are listed in the finding aid as multiple volumes. The collection also contains oversized volumes, in the form of large accounting books. These oversized volumes are numbered and stored separately. They are listed in the finding aid where intellectually appropriate, and designated by volume number. Enclosed in this finding aid is an index of the oversized volumes, organized by number, and their contents.
The collection is divided into six series: General University Financial Records; Trust Fund Records; Records of Land, Proposed Development and Construction; Operating Records of Buildings, Divisions and other Units; Miscellaneous Reports, Studies and Volumes; and Accounting Office Records.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Student housing.Student housing.; Dormitories--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Baird Carillon (University of Michigan); Barbour, Levi L. (Levi Lewis), 1840-1925.; Burton Tower (University of Michigan); Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies.; University of Michigan. Accounting Office.; University of Michigan--Administration.Administration.; University of Michigan. Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan--Buildings.Buildings.; University of Michigan. Controller.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan. Financial Operations.; University of Michigan--Finance.Finance.; University of Michigan--Students.Students.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.StudentsSocieties, etc.; University of Michigan--Gifts and loans.Gifts and loans.; University of Michigan. Institute for Social Research.; University of Michigan--Lands.Lands.; University of Michigan. Plant Operations.; University of Michigan. Secretary.; University of Michigan. University Hospital.; Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Students, Foreign--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; World War, 1914-1918--Education and the war.; World War, 1914-1918--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; World War, 1939-1945--Education and the war.; World War, 1939-1945--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Construction industry.; Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies.; Photographs.; University of Michigan. University Hospital.
Contributors:
Smith, Shirley Wheeler, 1875-1959.; Stone, Ralph, 1868-1956.; Christensen, John Cornelius, 1874-1952.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- General University Financial Records
  General University Financial Records, gives an overview of University funding and expenses. Included are the Secretary's journal of receipts and disbursements (1914-1949), various income records, and a number of verification and housekeeping records, including audits and inventories. Particularly interesting are a group of cash statements maintained throughout the Depression, apparently so that University officials could determine their ability to pay creditors.
  - Secretary's Journal of Receipts and Disbursements, 1914-1947
    - 1914-1918 (Volume 1)
      [No. 1]
    - 1918-1921 (Volume 2)
      [No. 2]
    - 1921-1924 (Volume 3)
      [No. 3]
    - 1924-1927 (Volume 4)
      [No. 4]
    - 1927-1930 (Volume 5)
      [No. 5]
    - 1930-1933 (Volume 6)
      [No. 6]
    - 1933-1936 (Volume 7)
      [No. 7]
    - 1936-1939 (Volume 8)
      [No. 8]
    - 1939-1943 (Volume 9)
      [No. 9]
    - 1943-1947 (Volume 10)
      [No. 10]
    - 1947 (Volume 11)
      [No. 11]
    - 1947-1949 (Box 1)
  - Income Records
    - State Funds
      - State Fund Ledger, 1931-1948 (Volume 51)
        [No. 51]
    - Gifts and Miscellaneous
      - Journals, 1890-1912
        [Nos. 17-18]
        - Journals, 1890-1912 (Volume 17)
        - Journals, 1890-1912 (Volume 18)
          (continued)
      - Gift Accounts Abstracts, 1903-1908 (Volume 19)
        [No. 19]
      - Gift Accounts Abstracts, 1903-1908 (Box 1)
      - Ledger of Alumni Contributions, 1932-1951 (Volume 49)
        [No. 49]
      - Rent Books, 1920-1929; 3 volumes (Box 1)
  - Verification and Housekeeping Records
    - Audits
      - Correspondence, 1928-1936 (Box 1)
      - 1940-1950, 8 volumes (Box 1)
        (1940, 1942, 1943 in box 23)
      - 1951-1964, 15 volumes; 1 folders (Box 2)
      - 1965-1976, 12 volumes (Box 3)
      - Annual Audits of Student Organizations, 19 volumes (Box 24)
    - Audit Reports of Michigan Auditor General
      - Ann Arbor Campus, 1965-1973; 2 volumes (Box 3)
      - Ann Arbor, Hospital, 1971-1973 (Box 3)
      - Dearborn Campus, 1972-1974 (Box 3)
      - Flint Campus, 1973-1975 (Box 3)
      - Condition of Funds, Monthly Report, 1933-1948; 5 volumes (Box 4)
      - Monthly Balances, 1928-1931 (Volume 50)
        [No. 50]
      - Bank Statements, 1931-1932 (Volume 48)
        [No. 48]
      - Cashier's Daily Statement, 1932-1934; 1 microfilms (Box 4)
    - Inventories
      - 1908 (Box 5)
      - 1916 (Box 5)
      - 1926 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous
    - College and Universities Financial Analysis, 1962 (Box 26)
    - Payroll Deductions, 1960-1961; undated (Box 26)
    - Questionnaires and Correspondence, 1924-1962; 19 folders (Box 26)
    - University of Michigan Organizational Charts, 1968 (Box 26)
  - Cost Center Sheets
    - 1990-1994 (Box 31)
    - 1994-1998 (Box 31)
  - General Fund Budget Reports
    - Control and Error Reports Activity Tracking, 1997-1998
    - Comparison and Summary Reports
      - 1989-1990 (Box 32)
        [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2029 ]
      - 1990-1991 (Box 32)
      - 1991-1992 (Box 32)
      - 1992-1993 (Box 32)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 32)
      - 1994-1995 (Box 33)
      - 1995-1996 (Box 33)
      - 1996-1997 (Box 33)
      - 1997-1998 (Box 33)
      - 1998-1999 (Box 33)
  - Hospital Financial Statements
    - 1954-1977 (Box 34)
    - 1978-1995 (Box 34)
- Trust Fund Records
  Trust Fund Records, includes extensive histories of the numerous trust funds operated by the University. Also included is conventional financial information regarding the investment and disbursement of trust funds found in journals (1923-1946), ledgers (1922-1945), securities records (1920-1950) and other books.
  - History (Box 6)
  - History, 2 volumes (Box 7)
  - Ledgers, circa 1920-1945
    [Nos. 28-34]
    - Ledgers, circa 1920-1945 (Volume 28)
    - Ledgers, circa 1920-1945 (Volume 29)
    - Ledgers, circa 1920-1945 (Volume 30)
    - Ledgers, circa 1920-1945 (Volume 31)
    - Ledgers, circa 1920-1945 (Volume 32)
    - Ledgers, circa 1920-1945 (Volume 33)
    - Ledgers, circa 1920-1945 (Volume 34)
  - Securities Records, circa 1920-1950
    [Nos. 35-38]
    - Securities Records, circa 1920-1950 (Volume 35)
    - Securities Records, circa 1920-1950 (Volume 36)
    - Securities Records, circa 1920-1950 (Volume 37)
    - Securities Records, circa 1920-1950 (Volume 38)
  - Receipt Registers, 1932-1948
    [Nos. 39-42]
    - Receipt Registers, 1932-1948 (Volume 39)
    - Receipt Registers, 1932-1948 (Volume 40)
    - Receipt Registers, 1932-1948 (Volume 41)
    - Receipt Registers, 1932-1948 (Volume 42)
  - Journals, 1923-1946
    [Nos. 43-45]
    - Journals, 1923-1946 (Volume 43)
    - Journals, 1923-1946 (Volume 44)
    - Journals, 1923-1946 (Volume 45)
  - Ledger, 1922-1940 (Volume 46)
    [No. 46]
  - Mortgage Register, 1897-1916 (Box 7)
  - Cashbook, 1928-1931 (Box 7)
- Records of Land, Proposed Development and Construction
  Records of Land, Proposed Development and Construction, contains records regarding property owned by the University, records regarding planned development of University property, and the actual construction of buildings for use by the University. Most significant is a series of Building Reports (1923-1930; 1936-1965) which documents in great detail the construction of every campus building erected during this period. In addition there is detailed information regarding many of these projects, particularly about the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies, the Baird Carillon in the Burton Memorial Tower, the Power Plant operating expenses and several dormitories. The dormitory files include correspondence with Ralph Stone and other University regents.
  - Land Records
    - Abstract and Plat of Walter Crane Farm, Detroit, 1906 (Box 8)
    - Land Contracts, 1902-1916 (Volume 52)
      [No. 52]
    - Inventory of Land Purchases and Major Construction, circa 1914-1930 (Volume 12)
      [No. 12]
    - Land Holdings in Ann Arbor Area, 1916-1931 (Box 7)
    - Homestead Lot and Lot "C" (Homeopathic Hospital), 1 folders; 1 oversize folders shelved in Bimu/B8/Out (Box 7)
  - Building Records
    - Summaries
      - Building Histories, circa 1940 (Box 7)
      - University Plant, 1894-1924 (Box 7)
      - Construction Costs, circa 1925 (Box 7)
    - Reports
      - Building Reports
        - 1912 (Box 7)
        - 1923-1930 (Box 7)
        - 1936-1946 (Box 7)
        - 1947-1957 (Box 9)
        - 1957-1962 (Box 10)
        - 1962-1965 (Box 11)
      - PWA
        - Progress Reports, 1938-1939 (Box 11)
        - Program Organization and Administration (Box 11)
        - Alleged Irregularities, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Individual Projects
      - Architecture Building, 1926 (Box 11)
      - Burton Memorial Tower, 1935-1938
        - Baird Carillon (Box 11)
        - Baird Carillon Site (Box 12)
        - William T. Mackie, Contractor (Box 12)
      - Children's Dentistry, 1938-1940; 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Dormitory Projects
        - Correspondence with Regent Ralph Stone, 1927-1936 (Box 12)
        - Correspondence with Other Regents, 1929-1933 (Box 12)
        - Residence Halls, 1944-1945 (Box 12)
        - Fletcher Hall, 1932-1933 (Box 12)
        - Men's Dormitory and Heating Plant, 1938-1940; 3 folders (Box 12)
        - Michigan Union, 1936-1941
          - Alan-Rumsey Financing (Box 12)
          - Architect (Box 12)
          - Wings A and C, Construction (Box 12)
          - Wings A and C, Refinancing (Box 12)
        - Mosher-Jordan, Financing, 1929-1947; 2 folders (Box 12)
        - Women's Dormitory, 1930-1938
          - Construction (Box 12)
          - Financing (Box 12)
          - Furnishings (Box 12)
      - East Engineering Building Roof Laboratory, 1941 (Box 13)
      - Health Service Building, 1938 (Box 13)
      - Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies, 1935-1938
        - Construction (Box 13)
        - Equipment Budget (Box 13)
        - Martin, D.R. Superintendent of Construction
          - Correspondence
            - A-B (Box 13)
            - C (Box 13)
            - D-H (Box 13)
            - I-O (Box 13)
            - P-W (Box 13)
            - W (Box 13)
            - W-Z (Box 13)
          - Inter-office Correspondence
            - April-November 1936 (Box 13)
            - November 1936-June 1937 (Box 13)
            - June-December 1937 (Box 13)
            - January-June 1938 (Box 13)
          - Daily Log of Construction, 2 volumes (Box 13)
        - Meetings (Box 13)
        - Site (Box 13)
        - Specifications (Box 13)
      - Hospital, 1922-1925
        - Building Program Bulletins, 3 folders (Box 14)
        - Thompson-Starrett Co. Audit (Box 14)
      - Hutchins Hall, 1930-1935; 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Medical Building, 1939 (Box 14)
      - Music, School of, 1938 (Box 14)
      - Neuropsychiatric Institute, 1937-1939 (Box 14)
      - Public Health, School of, 1941-1943
        - Construction (Box 14)
        - Financing (Box 14)
      - Rackham Educational Memorial, Detroit, 1939-1941; 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Social Service Space (hospital addition), 1938-1940 (Box 14)
      - University Elementary School, 1929-1937
        - Grant, General Education Board (Box 14)
        - Weekly Progress Report (Box 14)
      - University Museum, 1926 (Box 14)
  - Planning Documents
    - Expansion Program, 1920 (Box 14)
    - Reports on need for a new Administration Building, 1928-1939 (Box 14)
    - Report on need for new Service Building, 1941 (Box 14)
    - Post-War Expansion Program, 1943 (Box 14)
    - Educational Buildings Construction Program, 1948 (Box 14)
- Operating Records of Buildings, Divisions, and Other Units
  Operating Records of Buildings, Divisions and other Units, contains daily records regarding the functioning of a variety of University projects. A detailed list (1957-1964) of Departmental payrolls and accounts is available here. In addition, extensive dormitory records exist for most of the university-run housing facilities (ca. 1930-1965). The Board in Control of Athletics is represented (1932-1939), as well as the hospital (1925-1947), the Institute for Social Research (1946-1955), and miscellaneous student organizations (1932-1951). There is also detailed information regarding the operation of an exchange program between the University of Michigan and Waseda University in Tokyo, Japan. The Waseda University project files, found under the name of the project's sponsoring agency, the International Cooperative Administration, include detailed evaluations of the program written by Japanese participants just prior to their departure from the United States.
  - Departmental Payrolls and Accounts, 1957-1964; 6 volumes (Box 15)
  - Board in Control of Athletics, 1932-1939 (Box 15)
  - Dearborn Campus, Fairlane Apartments Housing Procedures, 1965 (Box 15)
  - Dormitory Records
    - Committee, 1945 (Box 15)
    - Journals
      - By Dormitory, 1933-1947 (Volume 13)
        [No. 13]
      - Martha Cook, 1943-1948 (Box 16)
      - Mosher-Jordan, 1930-1943 (Volume 16)
        [No. 16]
    - Operating Statements of Residence Halls
      - 1931-1948, 5 volumes (Box 16)
      - 1948-1954, 1960-1965; 10 volumes (Box 17)
      - 1965-1968, 9 volumes (Box 18)
      - 1968-1971, 3 volumes (Box 19)
  - Hospital
    - Journals, 1926-1947
      [Nos. 20-21]
      - Journals, 1926-1947 (Volume 20)
      - Journals, 1926-1947 (Volume 21)
    - List of Equipment and Furniture, 1925 (Box 19)
  - Institute for Social Research (Box 20)
    - Statements, October 1946-May 1955 (Box 20)
  - International Cooperative Administration
    - Atoms For Peace Program, Final Report, 1965 (Box 20)
    - Brazil Project (proposed), 1962 (Box 20)
    - Waseda University Program, 1956-1961
      - Contract
        - Draft Document (Box 20)
        - Background (Box 20)
        - Extension (Box 20)
      - Reports (regular)
        - December 1956 (Box 20)
        - June 1957 (Box 20)
        - December 1957 (Box 20)
        - June 1958 (Box 20)
        - December 1958 (Box 20)
        - June 1959 (Box 20)
        - December 1959 (Box 20)
        - June 1960 (Box 20)
        - December 1960 (Box 20)
      - Final Report, March 1961 (Box 20)
      - Reports Written in Tokyo (Box 20)
      - Supplemental Reports (Box 20)
      - Policy Meetings (Box 20)
      - Budgets (Box 20)
      - Seminars (Box 20)
      - Correspondence about Japanese Participants (Box 20)
      - U.S. Participants (Box 20)
      - Lectures of Stewart H. Rewoldt, 1960 (Box 21)
      - Lectures of Henry C. Smith, 1960 (Box 21)
  - National Inter-Fraternity Conference, Report to Regents (Box 21)
  - Student Organizations
    - Daily Record of Debits and Credits, 1931-1953; 6 volumes
      - 1951-1952 (Volume 22)
        [No. 22]
      - [A-L], 1952-1953 (Volume 23)
        [No. 23]
      - [M-Z], 1952-1953 (Volume 24)
        [No. 24]
      - [Q-Z], 1931-1951 (Volume 25)
        [No. 25]
      - [A-D], 1931-1951 (Volume 25)
        [No. 26]
      - [L-P], 1931-1951 (Volume 27)
        [No. 27]
  - University Committee on Annuities, 1934-1936 (Box 21)
  - University Committee on Army Contracts
    - Minutes and Information, 1948 (Box 21)
    - Contract Memos, 1942-1944 (Box 21)
    - Leases for Fraternity Houses, 1943-1945; 2 folders (Box 21)
    - General, 1943-1946 (Box 21)
  - Willow Run Airport
    - Manual of Operations and Procedures, 1953 (Box 21)
    - Accounts Receivable, 1950-1955 (Volume 47)
      [No. 47]
  - A Study of the Cost and Maintenance of Buildings and Grounds, 1924 (Box 27)
  - Buildings and Structures; A Statistical Record, 1978-1981; 4 folders (Box 27)
  - Electric Power Consumption, 1958-1960 (Box 27)
  - Equipment by Buildings, 1969-1976 (Box 27)
  - Major Buildings Constructed or Acquired, 1950-1960 (Box 27)
  - Power Plant